Mikleo!
ミクリオ！
（ミクリオ）あっ
わあっ…
（スレイ）
あれが 湖の乙女が住む都！
That must be where the Lady of the Lake lives!
We'll ride upon the wind to follow
Your path leading far off into the distance
The answers we seek won't be easy to find
We set out knowing that from the start
We wander endlessly to leave behind records of our dream
It's worth it if it widens our map of the world
Resound, O song of the wind
Should we forgo sight, the voices of our hearts will push us forward
We aim always ever higher
Carry, O song of the wind
Should we go without hearing, the voices of our hearts will stream forth
Emitting a dazzling radiance
Your azure melody rings true
（スレイ）すごい ミクリオ！
人が いっぱいだ！
Look at all these people, Mikleo!
ああ 確かにすごいな これは
Indeed, it's impressive.
This is a security checkpoint.
（ロゼ）検問待ちよ
（スレイ）おっ ん？
Well, what do we have here?
（ロゼ）はーん？ さては―
I bet you came here for the Sacred Blade Festival, huh?
今回の聖剣祭に合わせて
上京してきた人ね
You should hurry, though.
急いだほうがいいわよ
もうすぐ 一般の入場は
締め切る頃だろうから
Registration for the general public will close soon.
Yeah, but this crowd...
（スレイ）急ぐって言ったって…
You have a pass, right?
パスは持ってるでしょ？
（スレイ）パスって？
A what?
パス ないの？
Are you serious?
なくても
入れないわけじゃないけど―
I mean, they'll still let you in, but it'll take longer.
時間 かかるよ
（スレイ）えっ そうなの？
Really?
（ロゼ）ふむ…
Luckily, there's another way!
いい方法があるけど
（ロゼ）私たちは
通商条約に守られている商人
As merchants, we're protected by a free trade treaty.
We're the Sparrowfeathers.
“セキレイの羽”
どの街でも
フリーパスで入れるんだ
We can go pretty much anywhere we please.
へえー
これで 自由に街中を歩けるわよ
Now you're free to walk around town all you like.
Ahem...
はい
Huh?
何？
What do you mean, "huh?"
何って お金よ お金
500ガルド
That'll be 500 gald.
I don't do this for free, you know!
タダじゃないんだから
人間は お金が要るって
ジイジが言ってた
Gramps said humans need money.
You don't have money either?
お金もないの？
No...
（スレイ）うん…
（ロゼ）そんなわけないでしょ
Are you serious?
ちょっと それ 見せてよ
Lemme see your bag!
ええっ あの ちょっと
（ロゼ）うーん
H-Hey!
Now we're talking!
あっ いいもの 発見っと
I can't let you have that.
それはダメ
返さないといけないから
I have to return it.
（ロゼ）分かった 返す
All right, fine.
I have a feeling fate must've brought us together, so how about a rain check?
何かの縁だし
今回は １つ 貸しってことで
Looks like you're off the hook.
よかったな スレイ
うん ありがとう
All right, thanks!
So what do you think of Ladylake?
どう？
初めて見るレディレイクは
I know it's called "the aquapolis," but this is really something else!
（スレイ）水の都って聞いてたけど
想像以上だ！
Lively, huh?
にぎやかでしょう？
（スレイ）うん！
Yeah!
聖剣祭だからね
With the Sacred Blade Festival,
there are even more people than usual.
いつもより 人の数も多いよ
おおっと
のんびりしてる場合じゃなかった
Welp!
That's enough dilly-dallying for me.
I'm here in Ladylake on business, after all.
私たち レディレイクに
仕事しに来てるんだった
商売 商売
I gotta get back to work.
Enjoy the festivities.
あとは 祭りを楽しんでいって
うん いろいろ ありがとう
Thanks for everything.
Sorey...
スレイ 僕たちも そろそろ
アリーシャを捜さないと…
We should start looking for Alisha.
ミクリオ！
Mikleo!
The malevolence here is strong.
穢(けが)れがきつい
This city is teeming with malevolence.
ここ レディレイクは
穢れで満ちている
How are you feeling?
（スレイ）どうだ？ ミクリオ
Better now, thanks.
（ミクリオ）
ああ 少し落ち着いてきた
そっか
Good.
（ルナール）キヒヒ…
（スレイ）あいつ！
It's him!
Mikleo!
ミクリオ！
（ミクリオ）うっ
（ルナール）キヒャヒャッ
ハァッ
ええいっ
Sorey!
スレイ！
（ルナール）ぐっ… ああん？
（スレイ）うっ ぐうっ！ ぐ…
く… なぜ アリーシャを狙う！
Why are you after Alisha?!
（スレイ）イズチを襲ったのは
アリーシャが目的だからだろう！
You attacked Elysia to get to Alisha, didn't you?!
ケッ そっちかい
Oh, that.
俺が アリーシャ姫を
標的にすることはない
I'm not targeting Princess Alisha anymore.
（ミクリオ）
なら どうして ここにいる！
Then why are you even here?
Let's just say that I've taken a liking to her.
気に入ったからさ
あの お姫さんがな
近くにいれば
間違いなく 面白いものが拝める
I can tell that if I stick around her, there'll never be a dull moment.
But don't let your guard down.
だが 安心するなよ
（スレイ）はっ
（ルナール）
“俺が”やめたと言っただけだ
Just because I'm no longer targeting her doesn't mean no one else is.
誰からも狙われないとは
言っていない
It hasn't been called off, you know.
依頼は 今も継続されている
The hit on Her Royal Highness, that is!
姫殿下(ひでんか)を暗殺してほしいって
依頼がな
And as far as I know, the person they have on it always gets the job done.
あいつのことだ
引き受けた以上は
必ず 実行する
楽しみだねえ クヒャヒャッ…
I can't wait to see what happens.
（アリーシャ）先生
グリエルは その後…
Lady Maltran, has there been any word about Greil?
We couldn't find any survivors.
（マルトラン）
生存者は確認できなかった
What you told me is very hard to believe.
（マルトラン）
お前から聞いた話は信じがたい
（アリーシャ）全て事実です
It's all true.
Is that why you argued against
Chancellor Bartlow so adamantly?
（マルトラン）だからなのか
バルトロ卿に
あのような話をしたのは
聖剣祭に訪れた若者たちを―
You weren't just making a snide remark at their plans to
conscript the youth who attend the Sacred Blade Festival?
徴兵しようとする彼らへの
あてつけでなく
（アリーシャ）
いえ 本心です マルトラン先生
No, I was serious.
We shouldn't be waging war over resources.
今 やるべきは
戦争による奪い合いではありません
Even in victory, war breeds hate.
戦は 勝っても 憎しみを生み
負の連鎖は終わりません
And the spiral of hate goes on.
War doesn't have to be the answer here.
戦は いかなる理由であれ
やるべきではない
This is true even if the opposing side makes the first move.
それは 相手から
仕掛けてきたとしても―
同様であると考えます
The upper brass will never accept that.
しかし 軍のおもだったところは
了解するわけもない
Think before you act.
よく考えて行動することだ
（男性）それは事実か？
Oh, really?
I didn't think the princess was such a fool.
（バルトロ）
姫が ここまで愚かだとは
敵が攻めてきて なお―
The enemy fast approaches, and she orders us to stand down until we are attacked.
攻撃を受けてから
軍事力を行使するなどと
（男性）お前は それを
（バルトロ）もちろん 反対した
Did you object?
Of course I did.
しかし 姫は聞き入れなかった
But she would not listen to reason.
（バルトロ）さらに
アリーシャ姫がローランスと―
There are rumors floating around that Princess Alisha is secretly allied with the Rolance Empire.
裏でつながっているという話もある
（男性）戦いに消極的な
理由には 裏があるということか
That would explain her staunch opposition to the war.
（女性）
我々が ここに来た理由は―
The reason we've come here today is to determine whether Princess Alisha's assassination is justified.
王女アリーシャ暗殺の
是非を下すため
That decision will be made based on how many innocent lives can be spared by killing her.
そして それは―
殺しによって どれだけの民が
死なずに済むかという判断による
That is what the Scattered Bones consider to be honor.
我ら “風の骨”の矜持(きょうじ)だ
In that case...
であれば 間違いなく
姫がいることで―
There's no doubt that the princess's actions will lead our kingdom to ruin.
この国は
よからぬ方向へと向かっている
民は 姫の理想の犠牲になるのだ
She's trying to sacrifice the common folk in the name of her ideals.
姫の言葉で言うと
“専守防衛”と言うらしい
In her words, she wants an
exclusively defensive policy.
（女性）甘いね
How naive.
Chancellor Bartlow.
バルトロ卿
王女アリーシャの暗殺
改めて引き受ける
We accept your request...
to assassinate Princess Alisha.
Huh?
おっと
（マルトラン）５日間に及んだ
聖剣祭も いよいよ最終日だ
Today is the fifth and final day of the Sacred Sword Festival.
Now we begin the Rite of the Warrior.
これより 戦士の部へと入っていく
Huh?
（スレイ）あれ？
That's...
あれは…
There's no doubt about it.
間違いない
彼女 天族だ
She's a seraph!
That must mean...
（スレイ）ということは
あの人が 湖の乙女！？
She's the Lady of the Lake!
So that means the legends were true!
伝承は 本当だったんだ！
（兵士）ぬうっ
So much malevolence.
（ライラ）穢れが これほどまで
（ライラ）世界は もう…
The world is...
Ladies and gentlemen!
皆の者！
For the past several years, we have abstained from our beloved festival
この数年 我が国の伝統であった
聖剣祭も―
世相を鑑み 慎んできた
in light of the general state of the world.
But this year...
だが 今年は アリーシャ殿下の
全面的な支持のもと―
Thanks to the grace and assistance of our Lady Alisha, the Sacred Blade Festival can be held once more.
開催することができた
面白くなってきたあ
Now things are getting interesting!
Pulling out that sword means you're the Shepherd?
あの剣を抜けば 導師なのか？
It probably means that the Lady of the Lake recognizes you
（ミクリオ）おそらくは
湖の乙女に認められた者―
ということだろうね
導師の資格に足る者として
as someone worthy of being the Shepherd.
Worthy?
資格…
（兵士）ふんっ
これで最後か
Is that the last one?
姫は この茶番に
どう 落とし前をつけるのかな
How will the princess explain this farce?
What's Alisha gonna do?
アリーシャ 何かするのかな
Let us applaud the ten warriors and the rest of the participants.
（アリーシャ）まず
ここにいる10人の戦士と―
参加した全ての者たちに
拍手をお願いしたい
Unfortunately, we didn't the find the Shepherd at this festival.
（アリーシャ）今回の聖剣祭では
ついぞ導師が現れることはなかった
伝承によれば 導師とは
天族の力を借り―
According to the old legends, the Shepherd, with the aid of the seraphim,
will be the one to cleanse the world of malevolence.
この世の穢れを払う
救世主であるという
だが 私は 伝承を鵜呑(うの)みにして
この聖剣祭を開いたわけではない
However, I did not organize this festival because I blindly believed in the old legends.
今 我ら ハイランドと
隣国 ローランスは―
Today, our relations with our neighbors in Rolance are severely strained.
緊迫した状態にある
There are those who would believe that this festival is intended to raise morale before a war.
この聖剣祭を 戦の前の宴(うたげ)と
位置づける者もいるようだが―
But I must disagree.
私は そうは考えていない
The legends also tell of a time when
humans once coexisted with seraphim.
伝承には こうも記されている
“人は 天族を知覚し
共に暮らしていた”と
So instead of resolving conflict with war,
should we not strive to live in peace with others?
これは 戦で
争い合うのではなく―
他者と共に生きよと
示されているのではないだろうか
（ミクリオ）うっ
（スレイ）ミクリオ？
Mikleo!
That is what I believe.
（アリーシャ）私は思う
この災厄の今だからこそ―
Especially during these trying times...
Even if Rolance decides to invade,
we must not strike first.
仮に ローランスが
攻め込んできたとしても―
攻撃を受けるまで
我々から攻撃をしない
その勇気を持ちたいと思っている
We must be brave.
Such hostility.
穢れが…
The people's fear, dissatisfaction, and resignation are giving rise to so much malevolence.
この場にいる人々の恐れ 不満
負の感情から―
生み出されていく
This isn't good.
（マルトラン）まずいな
アリーシャ
Alisha!
何が起こっている
What's happening?
Sorey, we must get away from here!
スレイ ここから離れるんだ
That's a hellion!
あれは 憑魔(ひょうま)！
（男性）何だ？ 炎が！
What is that?! Look at the flames!
I have to...
あれは…
Sorey!
スレイ！
（スレイ）アリーシャ！
Alisha!
Sorey?
（アリーシャ）スレイ？
Sorey, what are you doing here?!
スレイ どうして ここに？
What's happening?!
一体 何が起こって
Can you guys not see it?
（スレイ）アリーシャたちには
見えてないんだね
Wait here!
待ってて
（アリーシャ）スレイ！
Sorey!
Lady of the Lake!
（スレイ）湖の乙女！
ハァッ…
（ライラ）あなたは？
Who are you?
I'm Sorey.
俺は スレイ
湖の乙女 あの憑魔を
何とかできないのか？
Lady of the Lake, can't you do
something about that hellion?!
Only the Shepherd can purify hellions.
（ライラ）憑魔を浄化することが
できるのは―
導師だけです
The Shepherd?
導師…
スレイ 君は もしや
本当に天族が見えて…
Sorey, you really can see seraphim, can't you?
（女性）ふんっ！
（アリーシャ）はっ
うっ！ ふっ…
（女性）ふんっ
アリーシャ！
Alisha!
Who are you?!
（アリーシャ）何者だ！
So long as you live, the people will suffer.
（女性）
お前がいれば 民が犠牲となる
What?!
なに？
（女性）ふっ！
Wait!
（バルトロ）待て
（マルトラン）ん？
The princess can handle herself.
姫ならば 自分の身くらい守れよう
それよりも
観客の避難を最優先にしろ
Your priority must be to evacuate the spectators.
Understand?!
分かったな？
You too!
お前たちもだ
That's an order!
これは 命令…
（一同）うわあっ！
（女性）ふんっ！
Stay away, Sorey!
来るな スレイ！
Don't worry about me!
私のことは気にするな
I need you to handle this situation!
それよりも この状況を
何とかしてほしい
It may be impossible for me, but you can do it!
私には無理でも 君ならできる
I just have this feeling.
そんな気がするんだ
Sorey, I beseech you!
スレイ 頼む！
Please wait.
（ライラ）お待ちください
Since you can see me, you must have a very strong resonance.
私の姿が見えるあなたは
きっと―
天族の縁(ゆかり)のある方なのでしょう
その剣(つるぎ)を抜くことも
できるかもしれません
Perhaps you can draw the Sacred Blade.
ですが その前に聞かせてください
スレイさん
However, let me ask you one thing, Sorey.
Why would you become the Shepherd?
あなたは なぜ 導師に？
May I ask you your name?
君の名前を聞いてもいいかな
（ライラ）
あっ はい ライラです
Oh, of course. I am Lailah.
（スレイ）ライラ
Lailah...
My dream is to investigate ancient ruins all over the world.
俺 世界中の遺跡を
探検したいんだ
古代の歴史には―
I believe that the old legends
hold knowledge about how humans and seraphim might one day live in harmony together.
人と天族が幸せに暮らす知識が
眠ってるって信じてるから
I must find a way to make that happen.
To bring humans and seraphim together again.
俺の夢は 人と天族が
幸せに暮らす方法を見つけること
If purifying the hellions will save both humans and seraphim...
憑魔を浄化することで
人と天族を救えるなら それは―
Then...
俺の追いかけてる夢と
つながってるんじゃないかって思う
Then it's the best chance I'll ever have to make that dream a reality!
だから ライラ
So, Lailah...
I...
俺は…
To become my sword is to serve as a vessel for me to dwell in and to assume the Shepherd's burden.
（ライラ）
剣を取るということは―
私を宿す器となり
宿命を背負うということ
浄化の力を操り
超人的な能力を得る代償に―
Blessed with the power of purification and abilities beyond human ken.
人に疎まれ―
Cursed to be scorned by others and wrought with despair.
心を打ちのめされることも
あるでしょう
To protect this land from the hellions means a constant stream of agonizing decisions.
時には 苦渋の決断を
迫られることも
It is a lonely battle, the likes of which you can scarcely imagine.
それは 想像を超えた
孤独な戦いです
（スレイ）それが 導師の宿命？
That's the burden of the Shepherd?
（ライラ）はい
Yes.
かまわない
It doesn't matter as long as it allows me to save these people here.
今 ここにいる人たちを
助けることができるなら
I believe the path of the Shepherd will lead me to my dream.
導師という道の先に
俺の夢が きっとあるから
I shall become...
俺は―
導師になる！
the Shepherd!
Fethmus Mioma...
（スレイ）“フォエス＝メイマ”
それが君の…
Is that your...
（ライラ）はい 私の真の名です
Yes, that is my true name.
Now, Sorey.
（ライラ）さあ スレイさん
Harness the overflowing power within you!
あふれる力を その身にとどめ！
Unleash the true power of the Shepherd!
導師たる 真の力を！
Now!
今！
Sorey is the Shepherd?
導師… 様？
バ… バカな！
Impossible!
スレイ！
Sorey!
If we close our eyes now,
here on this journey with no turning back,
we can find our moments of peace
and make our wishes as we sleep
I dreamed of the world
and the hope and warmth
that our devotion can give to it
We can stop and rest
for the morrow
and together
we can laugh
I'm sure we can fulfill our duties
at the end
of this long journey
For now, let us sleep
and dream of the future
Let us walk together
Next Time
Sorey, Mikleo...
I'm looking forward to our journey.
Lailah
So am I!
Sorey
...
Mikleo
Why don't you say something, Mikleo?
And what's with your face?
Sorey
You said to make a funny face for the next preview!
Mikleo
Oh, yeah. I forgot.
Sorey
Sheesh! Nice to meet you, Lailah.
Mikleo
Likewise.
Lailah
Tell me all about yourself, Lailah.
Sorey
Okay, ask away.
Lailah
What's your hobby?
Sorey
I like to fold origami and write letters.
Lailah
Do you like to cook?
Mikleo
I'm a fire seraph, so cookies are my specialty.
Lailah
So what does Fethmus Mioma mean?
Sorey
It means "Lailah the Pure."
Lailah
How much do you weigh?
Sorey
That's a secret.
Lailah
Your age?
Mikleo
Also a secret.
Lailah
What about next week's preview?
Sorey
That is too.
Lailah
The preview can't be a secret!
Mikleo
Next week: "The Shepherd's Destiny."
Don't miss it!
Sorey